A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, New Delhi, India Office, Office Files of Vanita Mukherjee FA661
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, New Delhi, India Office, Office Files of Vanita Mukherjee
1952-2016
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Mukherjee, Vanita Nayak
FA661
2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter size document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2021 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2021:082.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Strategy records, 1952-2016
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files that Vanita Nayak Mukherjee created when she served as a Program Officer for the Ford Foundation's New Delhi, India Regional Office. The New Delhi Regional Office oversees programming for the countries of India, Nepal, and Sri Lanka. Mukherjee's office files collection consists of one series of program strategy related records that concern the New Delhi Office's program strategy for sexuality and reproductive health in India as well as program strategy at the Ford Foundation in a broader sense.
Common materials found in the collection include correspondence, drafts, notes, reports, agendas, meeting minutes, other meeting materials, tables, procedure guidelines, and publications. In addition to the materials Mukherjee created during her tenure at the Ford Foundation from 2006 to 2018, there are also earlier records that she may have either received, inherited, or gathered. These materials appear to have been used to help inform Mukherjee's work with formulating program strategy, to get her acquainted with Foundation practices and procedures for grant making, and for the commemoration of the New Delhi Office's 50th anniversary in 2002.
India; Nepal; Sri Lanka; Ford Foundation; Reproductive rights; Reproductive health
- Strategy records, 1952-2016; 1; 2.66 Cubic Feet 7 letter size document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains an assortment of records that Ford Foundation Program Officer Vanita Nayak Mukherjee created and collected that primarily pertain to the Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Regional Office's sexuality and reproductive health program strategy in India as well as program strategy at the Foundation more broadly. Mukherjee's attendance and participation in various meetings and convenings related to program strategy are documented in materials like agendas, meeting minutes, summaries, correspondence, and notes.
  Much of Mukherjee's work with the New Delhi Office's sexuality and reproductive health programing appears to have aligned with the Foundation's Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights unit (SRHR). Documents in the series demonstrate the New Delhi Office's interest in preventing sexual violence, protecting sexual minorities, adolescent sexual and reproductive health and rights, and ending child marriage.
  Concerning the Ford Foundation's program strategy more broadly, there are materials in the series that document Mukerjee's role as a member of the Foundation's Strategy Advisory Group. There are also records that were created prior to Mukherjee's start at the Foundation that she may have used for training around Foundation practices and procedures for grant making. A significant amount of the materials that originate from before Mukherjee's tenure at Ford appear to have been compiled for the commemoration of the New Delhi Office's 50th anniversary in 2002, including a set of Program Letters authored by Douglas Ensminger, the first Ford Foundation Representative for India. These Program Letters describe Foundation program actions in India and the surrounding countries from as early as the founding of the New Delhi Office in 1952.
  The aforementioned material formats persist throughout the series to document other activities than Mukherjee's attendance at convenings. Additionally, there are drafts, procedure guidelines, tables, and publications.
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting, New Delhi, India, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ford Foundation convenings - Various global Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights unit (SRHR) meetings, 2009-2014 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Ford Foundation Global Sexuality Research and Advocacy Portfolio convening, Hanoi, Vietnam, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ford Foundation supported convening - Conference on Diversity and Co-existence in Asia, Kandalama, Sri Lanka, 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Philanthropy Learning Group (PLG) and Governance and Civil Society unit (GCS) meetings, Tarrytown, New York, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Global Social Justice Philanthropy learning meeting, New Delhi, India, 2004-2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation strategic engagement at World Social Forum (WSF), Mumbai, India, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office supported convenings, 2013-2015 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted – Open in 2025
  - Beyond Borders: Reproductive Health, AIDS, and Gender Violence as Global Issues, circa 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sexuality and Reproductive Health: Strategies for Programming, 2001 January (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office regional strategy papers, 2008-2009 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ford Foundation Worldwide Meeting, 2014 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights unit (SRHR) strategy, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Ford Foundation global strategy for civil society, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Program Officers Retreat, 2013 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - India regional strategy notes, 2014-2015 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office regional strategy, 2010-2015 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ford Foundation regional strategy documents, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sexuality and Reproductive Health and Rights unit (SRHR) Program Officers Meeting, Vienna, Austria, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Ford Foundation Strategy Advisory Group, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Sexuality, Reproductive Health and Rights unit (SRHR), 2011-2012 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - India regional strategy papers, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Restricted – Open in 2026
  - Ford Foundation strategy - Thematic Areas, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office program strategy, 2008-2016 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Visitors to Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office - Briefing documents, 2014-2015 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Grant Makers Orientation 2000 Notebook, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Ford Foundation Program Organizational Structure (POS) Design Group, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Program Officer Orientation, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Governance and Civil Society unit (GCS) Orientation Day, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Ford Foundation Guide to Foundation Actions 2004, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Ford Foundation Guide to Foundation Actions 2007 (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
  - Ford Foundation trainings and resources on communication, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - GBS2 User Training Guide, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Human Rights and Social Justice Program New Delhi, India Office active grants, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Political Activity and Lobbying Guidelines: U.S. Law Issues (New Delhi Office Refresher), undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Ford Foundation Grantmakers Resource Handbook, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office Statement of Current Issues, 2002-2003, circa 2002-2003 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Ford Foundation Grants to Indian Organizations: Administrative Guidelines, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Ford Foundation Grants to Organizations: Administrative Guidelines, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Ford Foundation Grants to Organizations: Administrative Guidelines, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Endowment Primer draft, 2000 March 16 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - New Directions in Grantmaking: Influencing and Leveraging Markets for Social Good, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Ford Foundation Endowment Working Group, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office 50th anniversary - Endowments, 1999-2001 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Response to complaint against grantee by ex-employee, 2002-2006 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Response to PRIA concern on new conditionalities, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Population Council - Promoting Adolescent Sexual and Reproductive Health and Rights in India: How Far Have We Come?, circa 2009-2010 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Girls Not Brides: The Global Partnership to End Child Marriage, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Core Group on Child Marriage, 2012 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Violence against women initiative by Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office, 2013 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ) budget, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Philanthropy: Ford's work in building philanthropy, 2002-2006, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Sexuality and Sexual Rights: Global Narratives and Conversations, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office 50th anniversary, 2000-2002 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - India Program Letters, 1953-1971 (Box 6, Folder 59-61)
  - India Program Letters, 1953-1964 (Box 6, Folder 62-63)
  - The Ford Foundation Self-Study of the India Program, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - The Ford Foundation and the CIA: A documented case of philanthropic collaboration with the Secret Police, 2001 December 15 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Ford Foundation New Delhi, India Office 50th anniversary - India Program Letters, 1952-1999 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - India Program Letters and reports, 1952-1965 (Box 7, Folder 67-68)